Register of the Romanov family papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Princess Natalia Konstantinovna (Constantinovna) Bagration-Mukhranskaia-Johnston photo album from carton no. 6, 1915-1941
  Box/Folder 37: 12-14
  Includes photographs depicting Grand Duchess Ksenia (Xenia) Aleksandrovna in England.
- Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Nikolaevich, materials collected by his grandson Prince Gavriil (Gabriel) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) from carton no. 6, 1881-1990
  - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Nikolaevich resignation file, 1881
    Box/Folder 37: 15
  - "Vypiski iz" pisem" Velikago Kniazia Konstantina Nikolaevicha k" Stats"-Sekretariu Golovinu," typescript, 1882
    Box/Folder 37: 16
  - Avtobiograficheskiia zapiski vysokopreosviachshennago Savvy, excerpts, Sergiev Posad, 1906
    Box/Folder 38: 1
    Account of Grand Duchess Aleksandra Iosifovna, Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), and Queen Olga Konstantinovna (Constantinovna) of the Hellenes visit to disgraced and exiled Grand Duke Nicholas Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) in Samara, as well as their visit to Tver'.
  - V" svietie istoricheskoi pravdy, N. Tal'berg, 1952
    Box/Folder 38: 2
  - Imperator" Nikolai I v" svietie istoricheskoi pravdy, N. Tal'berg, 1965
    Box/Folder 38: 3
  - Biographical notes on Grand Dukes Konstantin (Constantin) Nikolaevich and Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), 1950-1990
    Box/Folder 38: 4-8
    Includes writings, quotations, clippings, correspondence, and bibliography cards.
  - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) scrapbooks, documenting personalized historical record, 1891-1911
    - "Zhenskii pedagogicheskii institut"," "Bezporiadki: studencheskie, Vozstanie v" Moskvie, raznyia manifestatsii i t.d.,", 1891-1906
      Box/Folder 38: 9
    - "Akademiia nauk",", 1891-1910
      Box/Folder 38: 10
    - "Leib" Gvardii Izmailovskii polk",", 1891-1910
      Box/Folder 38: 11
    - "Literaturnyia perezhivaniia,", 1891-1910
      Box/Folder 38: 12
    - "O Rossiiskom" Imperatorskom" flotie,", 1894-1906
      Box/Folder 38: 13
    - "Raznyia puteshestviia,", 1895-1910
      Box/Folder 38: 14
    - "Raznyi material",", 1895-1911 (Reel 47)
      Box/Folder 38: 15
    - "Nachal'nik" voenno-uchebnukh" zavedenii,", 1899-1910
      Box/Folder 38: 16
- Dnevnik B. Velikogo Kniazia Andreia Vladimirovicha, redaktsiia i predislovie V. P. Semennikova, Leningrad, from carton no. 6, 1925
  Box/Folder 38: 17
- Memoirs of Princess Helen of Serbia (Helen Romanoff) from carton no. 6, circa 1960
  Box/Folder 38: 18
- Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) and other Romanov Family-related materials from carton no. 7, 1886-2002
  Includes printed matter, typescripts, manuscripts, and photographs, arranged chronologically.
  - General, 1950-1993
    Box/Folder 38: 19-20, 39: 1-2
    Includes copies of various publications in memory of Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) after his death in 1915.
  - "Elka u babushki v Anichkovie," essay by Prince Nikita Aleksandrovich, typescript, undated
    Box/Folder 39: 3
  - Essays in memory of Grand Duke Dmitrii Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), compiled by K. Skuratov, typescript, undated
    Box/Folder 39: 4
  - "Velikaia Kniaginia Elisaveta Mavrikievna po vospominaniiam" eia docherei," typescript, undated
    Box/Folder 39: 5
  - "Molitva" and "Na Strastnoi Nedielie," K. R., manuscript, Pavlovsk-Saint Petersburg, 1886-1887
    Box/Folder 39: 6
  - "O dietiakh", vypiski iz" pisem" Ego Imperatorskago Vysochestva Velikago Kniazia Konstantin" Konstantinovicha k" svoei sestrie Korolevie Grecheskoi Ol'gie Konstantinovnie," typescript, 1891-1908
    Box/Folder 39: 7
  - "Koronatsiia E. I. V. Gosudaria Imperatora Nikolaia II-go," typescript of an article from Niva, 1896
    Box/Folder 39: 8
  - Neotsienennoi pamiati skonchavshagosia muchenicheskoi smert'iu Velikago Kniazia Sergieia Aleksandrovicha, 1905, Archives of Americans of Russian Descent in Minnesota reprint, 1982
    Box/Folder 39: 9
  - Ego Vysochestvo Kniaz' Oleg" Konstantinovich", Boris Nikol'skii, 1914-1998
    Box/Folder 39: 10
    Includes pictures of Prince Oleg Konstantinovich and other related materials.
  - Svietloi pamiati Velikoi Kniagini Elizavety Feodorovny, Arkhiepiskop" Anastasii, Jerusalem, 1925
    Box/Folder 39: 11
  - "Rytsar' dolga, sviatoi liubvi i chistoi krasoty," S. Vil'chkovskii, typescript, 1926
    Box/Folder 39: 12
  - "Otviet Mitr. Evlogiia Metropolity Sergiiu," Vozrozhdenie, No. 836, Paris, 1927
    Box/Folder 39: 13
    Includes correspondence.
  - Zakonnyi Tsar' (Vopros" o nasliedii Rossiiskago Prestola), M. L. Bachinskii, Paris, 1937
    Box/Folder 39: 14
  - "O vstrechennykh mnoiu kul'turnykh gnezdakh v Rossii," doklad S. N. Smirnova v lagere Asten v Avstrii 28.7.1950 g. v den' Sv. Kniazia Vladimira i v den' russkoi kul'tury
    Box/Folder 39: 15
  - "K. R.," K. Solovskii (Solovsky), Paris, 1958
    Box/Folder 39: 16
  - "Velikaia Kniaginia Elisaveta Fedorovna," Prince Feliks Iusupov, typescript, 1966
    Box/Folder 39: 17
  - "Pamiati Vel. Kn. Dmitriia Konstantinovicha," Pravoslavnaia Zhizn', No. 3, New York, 1969
    Box/Folder 39: 18
  - Velikokniazheskaia usypal'nitsa v Petropavlovskoi kreposti, V. B. Gendrikov, booklet, 1993 (Reel 48)
    Box/Folder 39: 19
  - "Izmailovskie dosugi," N. N. Kalinin and M. A. Zemlianichenko, Dvorianskoe sobranie, Almanac, No. 3, 1995
    Box/Folder 39: 20
  - "The Constantines," Irina Bagration, circa 1995
    Box/Folder 39: 21
  - "Vospominaniia o vstrechakh s Velikim Kniazem Konstantinom Konstamtinovichem," B. Gorchakov, Nashi Vesti, Nos. 446-448, 1997
    Box/Folder 39: 22
  - Velikii Kniaz' Nikolai Konstantinovich, N. I. Nasledova, Society of Russian Former Cadets in San Francisco Bulletin, No. 64, 2000
    Box/Folder 39: 23
  - Imperial Russian Journal, a Modern Journal on the History of the Romanov Dynasty & Tsarist Russia, Volume 5, Nos. 1-2, 2002
    Box/Folder 39: 24
  - George Rome's photographs of Pavlovsk, Strel'nia, and Marble Palace, photo copies, circa 2002
    Box/Folder 39: 25-27
    Includes a short description of the images.
- Correspondence regarding Romanov Family from carton no. 7, 1923-1998
  - Adamovich, Boris, 1931
    Box/Folder 40: 1
  - Kantakuzin, Ekaterina (Katia), 1923
    Box/Folder 40: 2
  - Marie Romanoff, Princess of Russia, 1976
    Box/Folder 40: 3
  - Nicholas Romanovich, Prince of Russia, 1982
    Box/Folder 40: 4
  - Petrochenkov, Valerii V., 1998
    Box/Folder 40: 5
  - Shumskii, Anatolii Petrovich, 1995
    Box/Folder 40: 6
    Includes manuscript excerpts from the Grand Duke Konstantin Konstantinovich diaries, 1897-1912.
  - Tamara, Abbess, 1970
    Box/Folder 40: 7
  - Teimuraz (Teymuraz) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) Bagration, Prince, 1970-1986
    Box/Folder 40: 8
  - Zezulin, Elena (Lena), 1990
    Box/Folder 40: 9
    Includes a copy of the February 1921 report by N. Selezneff concerning the burial of Grand Duchess Elizabeth Feodorovna in Gethsemane.
- Romanov family-related materials from the grey binder, 1884-1969
  - Correspondence, 1884-1961
    - Aleksandra Iosifovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, Pavlovsk, 1887
      Box/Folder 40: 10
    - Alexander I of Serbia, 1885-1886
      - Chicherina, Aleksandra Aleksandrovna, 1886
        Box/Folder 40: 11
      - Tat'iana Konstantinovna (Constantinovna), Princess of Russia, 1885
        Box/Folder 40: 12
    - Alexander I of Yugoslavia to Princess Tat'iana Konstantinovna (Constantinovna), 1933
      Box/Folder 40: 13
    - Elena Vladimirovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, to Prince Teimuraz (Teymuraz) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) Bagration, 1954
      Box/Folder 40: 14
    - Elizaveta Mavrikievna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1911-1925
      - General, 1925
        Box/Folder 40: 15
      - Natal'ia Konstantinovna (Constantinovna), Princess and Prince Teimuraz (Teymuraz) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) Bagration-Mukhranskii, 1920-1924
        Box/Folder 40: 16
      - Tat'iana Konstantinovna (Constantinovna), Princess of Russia, 1911-1918
        Box/Folder 40: 17
    - Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), Grand Duke of Russia, 1884-1924
      - General, 1896
        Box/Folder 40: 18
      - Abamelek-Baratynskaia (Baratynskaya), Anna Davydovna, 1888
        Box/Folder 40: 19
        Includes a poem dedicated to Appolon Nikolaevich Maikov (Maykov).
      - Augusta, Princess of Saxe-Meiningen and Prince Moritz of Saxe-Altenburg, 1884-1914
        Box/Folder 40: 20-24
      - Buklevden(?), Karl Karlovich, 1910
        Box/Folder 40: 25
      - Elizaveta Mavrikievna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1907-1917
        Box/Folder 40: 26-28
      - Engelgardt, Baron, circa 1905
        Box/Folder 40: 29
      - Nicholas, Prince of Greece and Denmark, 1896-1899
        Box/Folder 40: 30
      - Vera Vasil'evna, 1914
        Box/Folder 40: 31
      - Unidentified, 1924
        Box/Folder 40: 32
    - Peter II of Yugoslavia to Prince Teimuraz Bagration, 1961
      Box/Folder 40: 33
    - Vil'chkovskii, Sergei, 1926
      Box/Folder 40: 34
    - Unidentified, 1887
      Box/Folder 40: 35
  - Prince Konstantin Aleksandrovich Bagration-Mukhranskii photographs, 1903
    Box/Folder 40: 36
  - Clippings regarding Romanov family, 1911-1969
    Box/Folder 40: 37
    Includes Niva, no. 40, 1915, dedicated to Prince Oleg Konstantinovich.
  - Russia 500 Rubles 1912 (2 banknotes)
    Box/Folder 40: 38
- Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) papers from the leather pouch, 1883-1920
  Arranged as originally received according to the "Inventory of letters in leather pouch" compiled by the donor. Includes correspondence, notes, and autopsy report.
  - "Brinz Friedrich von Sachsen-Meiningen," poem, circa 1890
    Box/Folder 40: 39
  - "Notitzen," brief biographical notes on Grand Duke Konstantin Konstantinovich, manuscript, undated
    Box/Folder 40: 40
  - Correspondence, 1883-1920
    - Albert I of Belgium, 1920
      Box/Folder 40: 41
    - Aleksandra Iosifovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1884
      Box/Folder 40: 42
    - Augusta, Princess of Saxe-Meiningen, 1883, 1915
      Box/Folder 40: 43
    - Elizaveta Mavrikievna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1917-1918
      Box/Folder 41: 1-3
    - Grand Duchess Elizaveta Mavrikievna's mother to her children (?), 1902 (Reel 49)
      Box/Folder 41: 4
    - Grand Duchess Elizaveta Mavrikievna's grandmother to her (?), 1891
      Box/Folder 41: 5
    - German Consul in Petrograd, concerning Grand Duchess Elizaveta Mavrikievna and her children, telegram, 1918 October 8
      Box/Folder 41: 6
    - Keller, Nina, undated
      Box/Folder 41: 7
  - Wedding of Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) and Princess Elisabeth von Saxen-Altenburg, printed notice, 1884 April 15
    Box/Folder 41: 8
  - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) autopsy report, 1915
    Box/Folder 41: 9
- Romanov family-related materials from the green file, 1948-1993
  - Opposition to marriage of Grand Duke Vladimir Kirillovich and Princess Leonida (Lida) Bagration Mukhranskii, 1948-1978
    Box/Folder 41: 10-13
    Includes correspondence, declarations, and clippings.
  - Materials relating to the restoration of the Grammar School on the outskirts of Alapaevsk, at the place of the execution of members of the Russian Imperial family in 1918, 1993
    Box/Folder 41: 14
- Prince Vladimir Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) Palei's writings from the green file, 1915-1996
  - "Tsar' Iudeiskii," by K. R., translated into French by V. Palei, 1915
    Box/Folder 41: 15
    Includes Niva, No. 7, 1914 and related materials.
  - Kniaz' Vladimir Palei. Poeziia, proza, dnevniki, compiled by Tatiana Aleksandrova and Liubov' Tiutiunnik, Moscow, 1996
    Box/Folder 41: 16-17
    Includes portrait of Prince Vladimir Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) Palei, 1916.
- Oversize materials, 1850-1995
  - Printed matter from carton no. 1, 1911-1928
    - Otechestvennaia Voina, 1812-1912 gg. Iubileinoe izdanie, Saint Petersburg (Reel 50)
      Box/Folder 42: 1
    - Kniaz' Oleg", Petrograd, 1915
      Box/Folder 42: 2
    - Prince Gavriil (Gabriel) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), copies of printed matter belonging to him, 1911-1912
      - Nastavnikam", khranivshim" iunost' nashu, Saint Petersburg, 1911
        Box/Folder 43: 1
      - Stolietnii iubilei Imperatorskago Aleksandrovskago, byvshago Tsarkocel'skago, litseia, Saint Petersburg, 1912
        Box/Folder 43: 2
    - Spisok" Abonentov" S-Peterburgskoi Gorodskoi telefonnoi cieti, 1913 (Reel 51)
      Box/Folder 44: 1
      Annotated in 1965 by Countess Xenia Czernichev-Besobrasov.
    - Kadet", Posviashchaetsia Avgustieishemu Kadetu Nasliedniku Tsesarevichu Aleksieiu Nikolaevichu, Izdanie Soiuza Rossiskikh" Kadetskikh" Korpusov", 1928
      Box/Folder 44: 2
  - Printed matter from Carton no. 4, 1901-1908
    - Sbornik" biografii Kavalergardov", 1724-1908. Po sluchaiu Stolietniago Iubileia Kavalergardskago Eia Velichectva Gosudaryni Imperatritsy Marii Feodorovny polka, by S. Panchulidzev, 4 volumes, 1901-1908 (Reels 51-53)
      Boxes 45-48 (Box 45 on Reel 51, Boxes 46-47 on Reel 52, Box 48 on Reel 53)
  - Printed matter from carton no. 5, 1951-1992
    - Vestnik kavalergardskoi sem'i, annual bulletin, 21 issues, Paris, 1951-1976 (Reels 53-54)
      Box/Folder 49: 1-21 (Folders 1-14 on Reel 53, Folders 15-21 on Reel 54)
      Missing: 1957 issue.
    - Point De Vue. Images Du Monde, No. 1471, 1976 (Reel 54)
      Box/Folder 50: 1
      Includes an article on Grand Duchess Maria Vladimirovna's marriage to Prince Franz Wilhelm of Prussia in Madrid on 22 September 1976.
    - Istoria Kavalergardov, by George Bibikoff, Paris, 1992
      Box/Folder 50: 2
  - Printed matter from carton No. 6, 1925
    - Dnevnik b. Velikogo Kniazia Andreia Vladimirovicha, 1913 god, Leningrad, 1925
      Box/Folder 50: 3
  - Printed matter from carton no. 7, 1995
    - Khram -pamiatnik moriakam, by S. N. Smirnov, reprint, 1995 (1915) (Reel 55)
      Box/Folder 50: 4
  - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) printed matter and photographs from the leather pouch, 1884-1930
    - "Dinner, 13 April 1884," Grand Duke Konstantin Konstantinovich's wedding reception menu, the Winter Palace in Saint Petersburg
      Box/Folder 51: 1
    - "Nasledstvo Velikoi Kniagini" (Grand Duchess Aleksandra Iosifovna's last will), 1890-1912
      Box/Folder 51: 2
      Includes Tseremonial" o sviatom kreshchenii Eia Vysochestva Tatiany Konstantinovny.
    - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) and family on the occasion of Silver Wedding Anniversary at the Pavlovsk Palace, 1909
      Box/Folder 51: 3
    - Princess Tatiana Konstantinovna (Constantinovna) at church special event, Saint Petersburg, 1910 September 14
      Box/Folder 51: 4
    - Prince Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) (?), circa 1910
      Box/Folder 51: 5
    - Prince Georgii Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), circa 1930
      Box/Folder 51: 6
  - Framed items from carton no. 2, 1850-1938
    Includes paintings, drawings, prints, and photographs depicting mostly Russian scenes, events, towns, and landmarks, as well as numerous portraits of royal Romanov family members. Arranged by size.
    - "Les quatre générations," custom picture frame with four miniatures of Princess Aleksandra Iosifovna, her daughters and granddaughter, circa 1890
      Box 52
    - Grand Duke Konstantin Konstantinovich (Constantin Constantinovich) in the role of Hamlet, performed in the private theatre of the Winter Palace, photograph, 1894
      Box/Folder 53: 1
    - Still life painting by Grand Duchess Olga Aleksandrovna, circa 1930
      Box/Folder 53: 2
    - Posieshchenie Sultana E.I.V. Velikim" Kniazem" Konstntinom" Nikolaevichem" v" Konstantinopolie v" 1845 godu, lithograph art print, circa 1850
      Box/Folder 54: 1
    - Count Mikhail Tarielovich Loris-Melikov (?), photograph, circa 1878
      Box/Folder 54: 2
    - Grand Duchess Olga Konstantinovna (Constantinovna) of Russia, portrait, circa 1910
      Box/Folder 54: 3
    - "Emperor Nicholas II and Grand Duke Constantin Constantinovich," photograph, circa 1910
      Box/Folder 54: 4
    - "Dvor" Ee Imperatorskago Vysochestva Blagoviernoi Gosudaryni Velikoi Kniagini Aleksandry Iosifovny," painting, 1910
      Box/Folder 54: 5
    - Prince Igor Konstantinovich (Constantinovich), photograph, circa 1915
      Box/Folder 54: 6
    - Prince Gavriil (Gabriel) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) and Antonina Rafailovna Nesterovskaya, photograph, 1938
      Box/Folder 54: 7
    - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Nikolaevich, photograph, circa 1860
      Box/Folder 55: 1
  - Clippings from red trunks nos. 1-2, 1914-1994
    - Romanov family, 1914-1994
      Box/Folder 55: 2
      Includes Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) obituary by Nikolai II in Pravitel'stvennyi Viestnik".
    - Various political events, 1927-1936
      Box/Folder 55: 3
    - Kidnapping of General E. Miller, 1937
      Box/Folder 55: 4
    - Yugoslav coup d'état against Hitler, 1941
      Box/Folder 55: 5
    - J’etais á Iékatérinenburg, par S. A. R. la Princesse Hélène de Serbie, Hélène Romanoff, Princess de Serbie, 1957 (?)
      Box/Folder 55: 6
    - The Fourth Congress of the Russian Foreign Cadet Corps, San Francisco, 1974
      Box/Folder 55: 7
  - Commemorative diplomas from red trunks nos. 1-2 given to Princess Vera Konstantinovna and Princess Tatiana Konstantinovna by the Russian Orthodox Church Abroad, 1938-1989
    Box/Folder 55: 8
    Includes Princess Vera Konstantinovna's family tree chart and seating chart for an unknown event.
  - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) negatives from the leather pouch, 1900-1909
    - Glass plate negatives, 1900-1909
      Not filmed.
      - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) and family on the occasion of Silver Wedding Anniversary at the Pavlovsk Palace, 1909 (Box-folder 56: 1)
      - "Papa michmanomie,", circa 1900 (Box-folder 56: 2)
      - "Marilly,", circa 1900 (Box-folder 56: 3)
      - Pavlovsk Palace (?), circa 1900 (Box-folder 56: 4)
      - "Papa vie vengerke,", circa 1900 (Box-folder 56: 5)
      - "Oleg vie Ostasheve,", circa 1900 (Box-folder 56: 6)
    - "Old negatives,", circa 1900
      - V. I Switzerland, 1-100 (Reel 55)
        Box/Folder 57: 1-6
      - V. II Sweden-Belgium-Switzerland, 1-100
        Box/Folder 57: 7-10
      - V. III Switzerland, 1-26
        Box/Folder 57: 11
  - Framed items from carton no. 2, 1875-1915
    - "Grand Duke Constantine as a young man,", circa 1875
      Box 58
    - "Unknown German relative,", circa 1900
    - Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) portraits, 1900-1915 (Boxes 59, 61)
    - Grand Duchess Elizaveta Mavrikievna, circa 1900 (Box 59)
    - Princess Augusta of Saxe-Meiningen, circa 1900 (Box 59)
  - Memorabilia from red trunks nos. 1-2, circa 1900
    - Kodak camera with case, belonged to Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) (Box 60)
    - Hand painted wooden Easter egg featuring family coats of arms that belonged to Grand Duke Konstantin (Constantin) Konstantinovich (Constantinovich) (Box 60)
    - Small items - pins, cufflinks, and buttons, property of Princess Vera Konstantinovna (Constantinovna) (Box 61)
    - House linens of Grand Duchess Aleksandra Iosifovna, Grand Duchess Elizaveta Mavrikievna, and Princess Vera Konstantinovna (Constantinovna) (Boxes 62-63)
    - Woman's Christian headcover (Box 64)
      Probably belonged to Princess Tatiana Konstantinovna (Constantinovna).
    - Umbrellas and canes that belonged to Grand Duchess Elizaveta Mavrikievna (Box 65)